Our world has many superheroes.
عالمنا مليء بالكثير من الأبطال الخارقين
But they have the worst of all superpowers: invisibility.
لكن هؤلاء يعيشون تحت واقع مؤلم: واقع التهميش
For example, the catadores,
مثلا "جامعو النفايات"
Catadores emerged from social inequality, unemployment,
ظهور فئة جامعي المخلفات انعكاس لعدم المساواة الاجتماعية والبطالة.
and the abundance of solid waste
فلوفرة النفايات الصلبة
from the deficiency of the waste collection system.
ولعجز الأداء الوظيفي لنظام جمع النفايات
Catadores provide a heavy, honest and essential work
فإن جامعي النفايات يقدمون عملا شاقا وصادقا وجوهريا
that benefits the entire population. But they are not acknowledged for it.
في خدمة لكافة السكان، لكن لا يُعترف لهم بذلك.
Here in Brazil, they collect 90 percent of all the waste that's actually recycled.
هنا في البرازيل، يجمعون 90% من النفايات المعاد تدويرها
Most of the catadores work independently,
معظم جامعي النفايات يعملون بشكل مستقل
picking waste from the streets and selling to junk yards at very low prices.
يجمعون النفايات من الطرقات، ومن ثم بيعها في ساحات الخردة بأسعار رخيصة للغاية
They may collect over 300 kilos
يجمعون ما يزيد على 300 كيلو
in their bags, shopping carts, bicycles and carroças.
في حقائبهم وعربات التسوق والدراجات والعربات البرازيلية
Carroças are carts built from wood or metal
العربة البرازيلية (carroça) تصنع من الخشب أو من معدن صلب
and found in several streets in Brazil,
وتوجد في عدة طرقات بالبرازيل
much like graffiti and street art.
في وضع مشابه جدا لفن الكتابة على الجدران والشوارع الجمالية.
I am a graffiti artist and activist
أنا فنان جداريات وناشط
and my art is social, environmental and political in nature.
وفني هو فن اجتماعي، بيئي وذو طابع سياسي.
In 2007, I took my work beyond walls and onto the carroças,
في عام 2007، انطلقت بعملي إلى ما هو أبعد من الجداريات إلى العربات البرازيلية "Carroças"
as a new urban support for my message.
كدعم حضاري لرسالتي.
But at this time, giving voice to the catadores.
في ذلك الوقت تم إيصال الفكرة لجامعي النفايات
By adding art and humor to the cause, it became more appealing,
بإضافة الفن والفكاهة لهذه القضية، فصارت أكثر جاذبية
which helped call attention to the catadores
مما سيجلب الاهتمام لجامعي النفايات
and improve their self-esteem.
ويرفع من احترامهم لذواتهم.
And also, they are famous now on the streets, on mass media and social.
فهم الآن من الشهرة بمكان: في الطرقات ووسائل الإعلام العامة والاجتماعية
So, the thing is,
لهذا الشيء،
I plunged into this universe and have not stopped working since.
فقد غرقت في هذا العالم ولم أتوقف عن العمل.
I have painted over 200 carroças in many cities
رسمت على ما يزيد من 200 عربة "Carroças" في عدة مدن
and have been invited to do exhibitions and trips worldwide.
ودعيت إلى إقامة معارض والسفر حول أنحاء العالم.
And then I realized that catadores, in their invisibility,
بعد ذلك علمت أن جامعي النفايات في قضية التهميش،
are not exclusive to Brazil.
ليست حكرًا على البرازيل
I met them in Argentina, Chile,
فقد اجتمعت بجامعي النفايات في الأرجنتين وتشيلي
Bolivia, South Africa, Turkey
وبوليفيا وجنوب أفريقيا وتركيا
and even in developed countries such as the United States and Japan.
وحتى أيضا في الدول المتقدمة كأمريكا واليابان.
And this was when I realized that I needed to have more people join the cause
لهذا أدركت أنني بحاجة إلى عدد كبير من الأفراد لينضموا إلى تلك القضية
because it's a big challenge.
لأنه تحدّ كبير.
And then, I created a collaborative movement called Pimp My Carroça --
بعد ذلك، أنشأت حركة تعاونية تدعى "عربتي الرائعة"
(Laughter) -- which is a large crowdfunded event.
(ضحك) - المُمولة بشكل ضخم جماهيري.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause).
(تصفيق)
So Pimp My Carroça is a large crowdfunded event
"عربتي الرائعة" هي حركة ممولة جماهيريرا بشكل ضخم
to help catadores and their carroças.
لمساعدة جامعي النفايات مع عرباتهم.
Catadores are assisted by well-being professionals and healthcare,
بالإضافة إلى مساعدتهم مهنيًا وصحيًا
like physicians, dentists, podiatrists, hair stylists, massage therapists
مثل تقديم خدمات من أطباء وأطباء أسنان وأطفال ومصففي شعر ومختصي تدليك
and much more.
وأكثر من ذلك
But also, they also receive safety shirts, gloves, raincoats and eyeglasses
بالإضافة، فإن جامعي النفايات يستلمون أيضا قمصانا وقفازات واقية ونظارات شمسية ومعاطف واقية من المطر
to see in high-definition the city,
حتى نرى المدينة بحق
while their carroças are renovated by our incredible volunteers.
في حين أن عرباتهم تُرمم عن طريق متطوعينا الرائعين.
And then they receive safety items, too:
أيضا فقد استلم جامعي النفايات عناصر للسلامة
reflective tapes, horns and mirrors.
كأشرطة عاكسة للضوء وأبواق ومرايا.
Then, finally, painted by a street artist
وأخيرا تم الرسم عليها عن طريق فناني الشوارع.
and become part of part of this huge, amazing mobile art exhibition.
لتصبح جزء من جزء من معرض فني ضخم ومدهش ومتجول أيضا.
Pimp My Carroça took to the streets of São Paulo, Rio de Janeiro and Curitiba.
مشروع "زيّن عربة القمامة الخاصة بي" انتقل إلى ساو باولو وريو دي جانيرو وكوريتيبا
But to meet the demand in other cities, including outside of Brazil,
ليصبح مطلب لمدن أخرى خارج البرازيل
we have created Pimpx, which is inspired by TEDx,
فأنتجنا مشروع (Pimpx) الملهم من برنامج (TEDx)
and it's a simplified, do-it-yourself, crowdfunded edition of Pimp My Carroça.
مشروع مبسط، يقوم بذاته، وهو صورة أخرى من مشروع "زيّن عربة القمامة الخاصة بي"
So now everybody can join.
والآن بإمكان كل واحد شخص الانضمام
In two years, over 170 catadores, 800 volunteers and 200 street artists
في سنتين، أكثر من 170من جامعي النفايات و800 متطوع و200 من فناني الشوارع
and more than 1,000 donors
وأكثر من 1000جهة مانحة
have been involved in the Pimp My Carroça movement,
انضمت إلى حركة "زيّن عربة القمامة الخاصة بي"
whose actions have even been used in teaching recycling at a local school.
التي اعتادت أن تصب أعمالها في تدريس إعادة التدوير للمدارس المحلية.
So catadores are leaving invisibility behind
لهذا فإني جامعي النفايات الآن يتركون التهميش خلفهم
and becoming increasingly respected and valued.
ليصبحوا أكثر احتراما وقدرًا
Because of their pimped carroças, they are able to fight back to prejudice,
لأنه، وبعرباتهم المزينة، قادرون على النضال في وجه الإجحاف
increase their income and their interaction with society.
بزيادة دخلهم المادي وبتفاعلهم في المجتمع.
So now, I'd like to challenge you to start looking at and acknowledging
أما الآن فإنني أتحداكم أن تعيدوا النظر في الاعتراف
the catadores and other invisible superheroes from your city.
بجامعي النفايات وغيرهم من الأبطال المخفيين في مدينتك.
Believe it or not,
فلتؤمن بهذا أو لا
there are over 20 million catadores worldwide.
ففي العالم ما يزيد على 20 مليون من جامعي النفايات
So next time you see one,
فستشاهد واحدًا منهم
recognize them as a vital part of our society.
اعترف بهم كجزء حيوي من مجتمعك
Muito obrigado, thank you.
شكرًا جزيلا.
(Applause).
(تصفيق).